A Guide to the Editorial Cartoons of Bob Gorrell, 1978-2001
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Editorial Cartoons of Bob Gorrell 1978-2001
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12424
There are 850 items in 6 boxes, equaling ca. 2 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library by Bob Gorrell, Richmond, Virginia, on November 16, 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
Bob Gorrell graduated Phi Beta Kappa from the University of Virginia in 1977. He worked for two years at the Fort Meyers News-Press in Florida, and then moved to Charlotte, North Carolina to work for the Charlotte News. In 1983 he began working for the Richmond News Leader in Richmond, Virginia, and then for the Richmond Times-Dispatch in 1992. In 1998 he resigned from the Richmond Times-Dispatch in order to focus on syndicated editorial cartoons and comic panel features for Creators Syndicate. From November 2000 until August 2001, Gorrell served as editor at iPipe, Inc., where he managed the distribution of feature content to major Internet portals and where he developed the editorial cartoon site Edivu, which was named a Best of the Web winner by U.S. News & World Report. In October 2001, Gorrell was named Editorial Cartoonist for America Online News, giving him one of the nation's largest daily audiences through that outlet's 33 million subscribers.
Gorrell's work has appeared through syndication in hundreds of daily and weekly newspapers, including The Atlanta Journal, The Portland Oregonian, The Providence Journal, USA Today, The New York Post, The Washington Times, The Wall Street Journal and The New York Times. His commentary has been featured in Time, Newsweek, National Review, and other prominent periodicals, and college papers receive his drawings through the U.S.I.C. Educational Foundation. Gorrell cartoons have been used on CBS television's Face the Nation and on C-Span, and he himself has guested on CNN's Crossfire as well as other television and radio broadcasts. His work has been included in numerous cartoon anthologies, and is available along with cartoons by Gary Brookins in their jointly-published Pen Pals. During 1995, Gorrell compiled a solo collection of his cartoons for national distribution titled Affairs of State.
He has won awards and citations for excellence from the Overseas Press Club of America, the Fischetti Editorial Cartoon Competition, the Mencken Awards, the Virginia Press Association, and the Dragonslayer Editorial Cartoon Contest. He also won the 1998 National Press Foundation Berryman Award for editorial cartoonist of the year. His cartoons have been published in over 400 different newspapers and magazines.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the editorial cartoons of Bob Gorrell; the cartoons included are mainly original drawings, with some photocopies and one aluminum plate. Bob Gorrell's career as an editorial cartoonist began in 1977 at the Fort Meyers News-Press in Florida; he has since worked at the Charlotte News, Richmond News Leader, and Richmond Times-Dispatch. Since 1998, he has worked on syndicated cartoons for Creators Syndicate.
There are 850 items in 6 boxes, equaling ca. 2 linear feet. Documents in the collection range from 1978 to 2001, although the bulk occurs from 1978 to 1979 and from 1996 to 2001.
Topics include the presidential elections of 1980, 1996 and 2000; the Equal Rights Amendment; the economy, inflation and taxes; the budget; energy policies; foreign relations, particularly with Middle Eastern nations and China; Kosovo; tobacco industry; gun control; and the internet.
Also Menachem Begin; Pat Buchanan; George W. Bush; Jimmy Carter; Bill and Hillary Clinton; Elian Gonzales; Al Gore; Saddam Husseim; John McCain; Ronald Reagan; Anwar Sadat; and O.J. Simpson.
Arrangement
This collection is organized chronologically by year, and then alphabetically by subject matter within years.
Contents List
- Africa 1978 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Bureaucracy 1978 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Jimmy Carter 1978 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Jimmy Carter and Congress 1978 (Box-folder 1:4)
- China 1978 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Civil Service 1978 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Economy: Budget, Taxes 1978 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Economy: Inflation 1978 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Economy: miscellaneous 1978 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Election: 1980 1978 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Energy Policy 1978 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) 1978 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Florida 1978 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Health Care 1978 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Labor Reform 1978 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Middle East 1978 (Box-folder 1:16)
- Miscellaneous 1978 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Oil 1978 (Box-folder 1:18)
- Postal Service 1978 (Box-folder 1:19)
- USSR-US Relations 1978 (Box-folder 1:20)
- Budget, Taxes 1979 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Jimmy Carter-miscellaneous 1979 (Box-folder 2:2)
- China 1979 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Energy Crisis, Oil 1979 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Inflation 1979 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Middle East 1979 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Miscellaneous 1979 (Box-folder 2:7)
- SALT II (Strategic Arms Limitation talks) 1979 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Cartoon on Aluminum- Ronald Reagan and El Salvador 1982 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Miscellaneous Cartoons 1984 (Box-folder 2:10)
- Miscellaneous Cartoons 1985 (Box-folder 2:11)
- Miscellaneous Cartoons 1986 (Box-folder 2:12)
- Abortion 1996 (Box-folder 2:13)
- Airline Safety 1996 (Box-folder 2:14)
- Armed Forces, CIA 1996 (Box-folder 2:15)
- Arthur Ashe 1996 (Box-folder 2:16)
- Hillary Clinton 1996 (Box-folder 2:17)
- Clinton Scandals 1996 (Box-folder 2:18)
- Domestic Issues 1996 (Box-folder 2:19)
- Domestic Terrorism, Fear 1996 (Box-folder 2:20)
- Election: Pat Buchanan 1996 (Box-folder 2:21)
- Election: Bill Clinton 1996 (Box-folder 2:22)
- Election Bob Dole 1996 (Box-folder 2:23)
- Election: General 1996 (Box-folder 2:24)
- Election: Miscellaneous Candidates 1996 (Box-folder 2:25)
- Financial Issues 1996 (Box-folder 2:26)
- Foreign Affairs 1996 (Box-folder 2:27)
- Holidays and Weather 1996 (Box-folder 2:28)
- Media and Entertainment 1996 (Box-folder 2:29)
- The Olympics 1996 (Box-folder 2:30)
- Schools, Children 1996 (Box-folder 2:31)
- Marge Schott, Baseball 1996 (Box-folder 2:32)
- O. J. Simpson Trial 1996 (Box-folder 2:33)
- Technology 1996 (Box-folder 2:34)
- Tobacco Industry 1996 (Box-folder 2:35)
- Miscellaneous Cartoons 1997 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Campaign Finance 1998 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Clinton Approval Ratings 1998 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Clinton Scandal 1998 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Cloning 1998 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Democratic Party 1998 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Education, Child Care 1998 (Box-folder 3:7)
- Elections 1998 (Box-folder 3:8)
- Foreign Affairs: Miscellaneous 1998 (Box-folder 3:9)
- Gingrich Controversy 1998 (Box-folder 3:10)
- Al Gore 1998 (Box-folder 3:11)
- The Internet 1998 (Box-folder 3:12)
- Iraq 1998 (Box-folder 3:13)
- Dr. Kevorkian 1998 (Box-folder 3:14)
- Kosovo 1998 (Box-folder 3:15)
- Markets, Economy 1998 (Box-folder 3:16)
- Media 1998 (Box-folder 3:17)
- Mergers 1998 (Box-folder 3:18)
- Microsoft 1998 (Box-folder 3:19)
- Middle East 1998 (Box-folder 3:20)
- Military Readiness 1998 (Box-folder 3:21)
- Nuclear Testing 1998 (Box-folder 3:22)
- Lewis Powell 1998 (Box-folder 3:23)
- Social Securuty 1998 (Box-folder 3:24)
- Sports 1998 (Box-folder 3:25)
- Taxes, Budget 1998 (Box-folder 3:26)
- Tobacco Legislation 1998 (Box-folder 3:27)
- Weather 1998 (Box-folder 3:28)
- Art and Media 1999 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Budget Issues, Taxes 1999 (Box-folder 4:2)
- China 1999 (Box-folder 4:3)
- Hillary Clinton 1999 (Box-folder 4:4)
- Clinton Legacy 1999 (Box-folder 4:5)
- Clinton Scandal 1999 (Box-folder 4:6)
- Court Cases: Miscellaneous 1999 (Box-folder 4:7)
- Election: Pat Buchanan 1999 (Box-folder 4:8)
- Election: George W. Bush 1999 (Box-folder 4:9)
- Election: Al Gore 1999 (Box-folder 4:10)
- Election: John McCain 1999 (Box-folder 4:11)
- Election: Miscellaneous 1999 (Box-folder 4:12)
- Elian Gonzales 1999 (Box-folder 4:13)
- Gun Control, Violence 1999 (Box-folder 4:14)
- Health Care 1999 (Box-folder 4:15)
- Dr. Kevorkian 1999 (Box-folder 4:16)
- Kosovo 1999 (Box-folder 4:17)
- Legislation and Initiatives: Miscellaneous 1999 (Box-folder 4:18)
- Middle East 1999 (Box-folder 4:19)
- NASA Mars Mission 1999 (Box-folder 4:20)
- NBA (National Basketball Association) 1999 (Box-folder 4:21)
- Olympic Committee Scandal 1999 (Box-folder 4:22)
- Janet Reno 1999 (Box-folder 4:23)
- Republican Congress 1999 (Box-folder 4:24)
- Schools 1999 (Box-folder 4:25)
- Stock Market 1999 (Box-folder 4:26)
- Technology 1999 (Box-folder 4:27)
- Terrorism, Clemency 1999 (Box-folder 4:28)
- United States Peacekeeping 1999 (Box-folder 4:29)
- World Bank 1999 (Box-folder 4:30)
- Y2K 1999 (Box-folder 4:31)
- Boris Yeltsin 1999 (Box-folder 4:32)
- Abortion 2000 (Box-folder 5:1)
- Boy Scouts of America 2000 (Box-folder 5:2)
- Cell Phones 2000 (Box-folder 5:3)
- China 2000 (Box-folder 5:4)
- Bill Clinton 2000 (Box-folder 5:5)
- Hillary Clinton 2000 (Box-folder 5:6)
- Economy and Taxes 2000 (Box-folder 5:7)
- Education and Schools 2000 (Box-folder 5:8)
- Election: George W. Bush, Republican Party 2000 (Box-folder 5:9)
- Election: General 2000 (Box-folder 5:10)
- Election: Al Gore, Democratic Party 2000 (Box-folder 5:11)
- Election: Alan Keyes 2000 (Box-folder 5:12)
- Election: John McCain 2000 (Box-folder 5:13)
- Election: Recall 2000 (Box-folder 5:14)
- Entertainment, Media 2000 (Box-folder 5:15)
- Elian Gonzales 2000 (Box-folder 5:16)
- Foreign Policy 2000 (Box-folder 5:17)
- Gun Control 2000 (Box-folder 5:18)
- Human Genome Project 2000 (Box-folder 5:19)
- The Internet, Technology 2000 (Box-folder 5:20)
- Bob Knight-Indiana University Basketball 2000 (Box-folder 5:21)
- In Memoriam 2000 (Box-folder 5:22)
- Microsoft 2000 (Box-folder 5:23)
- Middle East 2000 (Box-folder 5:24)
- Nuclear Weapons 2000 (Box-folder 5:25)
- Oil Prices 2000 (Box-folder 5:26)
- Vladimir Putin 2000 (Box-folder 5:27)
- South Carolina Flag 2000 (Box-folder 5:28)
- Tobacco Regulation 2000 (Box-folder 5:29)
- WTO Protests 2000 (Box-folder 5:30)
- John Ashcroft 2001 (Box-folder 6:1)
- George W. Bush 2001 (Box-folder 6:2)
- China-United States Relations 2001 (Box-folder 6:3)
- Bill Clinton 2001 (Box-folder 6:4)
- Tom Daschle 2001 (Box-folder 6:5)
- Economy and Taxes 2001 (Box-folder 6:6)
- Education, Schools 2001 (Box-folder 6:7)
- The Environment, Energy 2001 (Box-folder 6:8)
- Foreign Affairs: Miscellaneous 2001 (Box-folder 6:9)
- The Internet 2001 (Box-folder 6:10)
- Jesse Jackson 2001 (Box-folder 6:11)
- Jim Jeffords 2001 (Box-folder 6:12)
- John McCain 2001 (Box-folder 6:13)
- McCain-Feingold Act 2001 (Box-folder 6:14)
- Timothy McVeigh 2001 (Box-folder 6:15)
- Middle East 2001 (Box-folder 6:16)
- Political Correctness 2001 (Box-folder 6:17)
- Racial Tensions 2001 (Box-folder 6:18)
- Space Defense Program 2001 (Box-folder 6:19)
- Miscellaneous Cartoons n.d. (Box-folder 6:20)